Jenni Chang: When I told my parents I was gay,
جيني: عندما أخبرت والداي أنني مثلية،
the first thing they said to me was,
أول شيء قالاه هو،
"We're bringing you back to Taiwan."
"سنعيدك إلى تايوان"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In their minds, my sexual orientation was America's fault.
بالنسبة لهما، يعتبر توجهي الجنسي خطأ أمريكا.
The West had corrupted me with divergent ideas,
أفسدني الغرب بأفكاره المنحرفة،
and if only my parents had never left Taiwan,
ولولا مغادرة عائلتي لتايوان،
this would not have happened to their only daughter.
لما حصل هذا لابنتهما الوحيدة.
In truth, I wondered if they were right.
في حقيقة الأمر، تساءلت إن كانوا محقين في ذلك.
Of course, there are gay people in Asia,
يوجد بالتأكيد العديد من المثليين في آسيا،
just as there are gay people in every part of the world.
مثلما يوجد العديد منهم في كل جزء من العالم.
But is the idea of living an "out" life,
ولكن هل تعتبر فكرة العيش على الملئ ،
in the "I'm gay, this is my spouse, and we're proud of our lives together"
وتعلن للناس هذا: "أنا مثلي وهذه زوجتي ونفتخر بعيشنا معا."
kind of way just a Western idea?
من ذلك النوع من الأفكار الغربية؟
If I had grown up in Taiwan, or any place outside of the West,
إذا نشأت في تايوان أو أي مكان آخر خارج الغرب،
would I have found models of happy, thriving LGBT people?
هل كنت سأجد نماذج من أشخاص مثليين سعداء ويعيشون حياة مزدهرة؟
Lisa Dazols: I had similar notions.
ليزا: كانت لدي نفس المفاهيم.
As an HIV social worker in San Francisco,
كأخصائية إجتماعية للمصابين بالإيدز في سان فرانسيسكو،
I had met many gay immigrants.
قابلت العديد من المهاجرين المثليين.
They told me their stories of persecution in their home countries,
أخبروني قصصهم من الاضطهاد الذي تعرضوا إليه في مسقط رأسهم،
just for being gay,
فقط لكونهم مثلييَ الجنس،
and the reasons why they escaped to the US.
والسبب من لجوئهم إلى الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية.
I saw how this had beaten them down.
رأيت العلامات التي خلفها الضرب المبرح.
After 10 years of doing this kind of work,
بعد 10 سنوات من ممارستي لهذا العمل،
I needed better stories for myself.
اقتنعت أنني بحاجة لقصص أفضل.
I knew the world was far from perfect,
أعرف أن العالم بعيد عن الكمال،
but surely not every gay story was tragic.
لكن بالتأكيد ليست كل قصص الشواذ مأساويةً.
JC: So as a couple, we both had a need to find stories of hope.
جيني: كزوجين، كلانا كان في حاجة لإيجاد قصص تبعث فينا الأمل.
So we set off on a mission to travel the world
لذلك، قمنا بالتخطيط للسفر حول العالم
and look for the people we finally termed as the "Supergays."
والبحث عن أشخاص أطلقنا عليهم اسم "المثليين الخارقين"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
These would be the LGBT individuals
سيكون هؤلاء من الفئة
who were doing something extraordinary in the world.
التي قامت بشئٍ استثنائي للعالم.
They would be courageous, resilient,
سيكون من الذين يتحلون بالشجاعة والمرونة،
and most of all, proud of who they were.
والأهم من ذلك، فخورين بما هم عليه.
They would be the kind of person that I aspire to be.
يعتبرون مثلي الأعلى وما أطمح أن أكون عليه.
Our plan was to share their stories to the world through film.
كانت خطتنا أن ننشر قصصهم للعالم من خلال فيلم نقوم بتصويره.
LD: There was just one problem.
ليزا: كانت هناك مشكلة واحدة فقط.
We had zero reporting and zero filmmaking experience.
كنا لا نملك أي خبرة في تقديم التقارير ولا في صناعة الأفلام.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We didn't even know where to find the Supergays,
لم نكن نعرف أين يمكننا إيجادهم،
so we just had to trust that we'd figure it all out along the way.
كنا علينا أن نثق بأننا سنجد حلا خلال هذه الرحلة.
So we picked 15 countries in Asia, Africa and South America,
قمنا باختيار 15 بلدا من آسيا وأفريقيا وأمريكا الجنوبية،
countries outside the West that varied in terms of LGBT rights.
بلاد من خارج الغرب والتي تتسم بتنوع من حيث حقوق المثليين.
We bought a camcorder,
اشترينا كاميرا فيديو،
ordered a book on how to make a documentary --
واقتنينا كتابا حول كيفية صنع فيلم وثائقي،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
you can learn a lot these days --
يمكنك أن تتعلم الكثير هذه الأيام،
and set off on an around-the-world trip.
وانطلقنا في رحلة حول العالم.
JC: One of the first countries that we traveled to was Nepal.
جيني: نيبال هي أول وجهة قصدناها.
Despite widespread poverty, a decade-long civil war,
بالرغم من الفقر المنتشر والحرب الأهلية التي دامت عقدا من الزمن،
and now recently, a devastating earthquake,
والزلزال المدمر الذي ضرب البلاد مؤخرا،
Nepal has made significant strides in the fight for equality.
حققت نيبال تقدما كبيرا في نضالها من أجل تحقيق المساواة.
One of the key figures in the movement is Bhumika Shrestha.
تعتبر بوميكا شريسنا من الوجوه البارزة في الحركة.
A beautiful, vibrant transgendered woman,
امرأة متحولة جنسيا جميلة ونابضة بالحياة،
Bhumika has had to overcome being expelled from school
تغلبت بوميكا على صدمة طردها من المدرسة
and getting incarcerated because of her gender presentation.
وسجنها بسبب مظهرها الخارجي المتناقض لجنسها.
But, in 2007, Bhumika and Nepal's LGBT rights organization
ولكن في عام 2007، نجحت بوميكا ومنظمة حقوق "إل جي بي تي" بنيبال
successfully petitioned the Nepali Supreme Court
في تقديم عريضة للمحكمة العليا بنيبال
to protect against LGBT discrimination.
لحمايتهم من التمييز.
Here's Bhumika:
هذه بوميكا تتحدث:
(Video) BS: What I'm most proud of?
(فيديو) بوميكا: ماهو أكبر مصدر للفخر؟
I'm a transgendered person.
أنا شخص متحول جنسيا.
I'm so proud of my life.
أنا فخورة بحياتي.
On December 21, 2007,
في 21 ديسمبر من عام 2007،
the supreme court gave the decision for the Nepal government
أصدرت المحكمة العليا قرار لحكومة نيبال
to give transgender identity cards
باستخراج بطاقات هوية للمتحولين جنسيا
and same-sex marriage.
وبقبول الزواج من نفس الجنس.
LD: I can appreciate Bhumika's confidence on a daily basis.
ليزا: يمكنني أن أقدر ثقة بوميكا على أساس يومي.
Something as simple as using a public restroom
شيء بسيط مثل استخدام المراحيض العامة
can be a huge challenge when you don't fit in
يمكن أن يشكل ذلك تحديا كبيرا عندما لا تتناسب
to people's strict gender expectations.
مع توقعات الناس المتشددة حول الجنس.
Traveling throughout Asia,
بالسفر في أنحاء آسيا،
I tended to freak out women in public restrooms.
أتسبب بإخافة النساء في المراحيض العامة.
They weren't used to seeing someone like me.
لم تكن معتادات على رؤية شخص مثلي.
I had to come up with a strategy, so that I could just pee in peace.
واضطررت إلى إيجاد استراتيجية لأتمكن من قضاء حاجتي بسلام.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So anytime I would enter a restroom,
في أي وقت أود فيه دخول المرحاض،
I would thrust out my chest to show my womanly parts,
أقوم بدفع صدري إلى الأمام وإظهار قليل من مفاتني،
and try to be as non-threatening as possible.
وأحاول أن لا أكون تهديدا لهم قدر الإمكان.
Putting out my hands and saying, "Hello",
أرفع يدي وأحييهم،
just so that people could hear my feminine voice.
حتى يتمكن الناس من سماع صوتي الأنثوي.
This all gets pretty exhausting, but it's just who I am.
هذا الأمر مرهق للغاية ولكن هذه أنا.
I can't be anything else.
لا يمكنني أن أكون أي شيء آخر.
JC: After Nepal, we traveled to India.
جيني: بعد نيبال، سافرنا نحو الهند.
On one hand, India is a Hindu society,
من جهة، تعتبر الهند مجتمعا هندوسيًا،
without a tradition of homophobia.
بدون وجود أي تقليد لرهاب المثلية.
On the other hand, it is also a society with a deeply patriarchal system,
من جهة أخرى، يعتبر مجتمعا بنظام أبوي صارم.
which rejects anything that threatens the male-female order.
يرفض أي شيء قد يهدد النظام المتبع بين الذكر والأنثى.
When we spoke to activists,
عندما تحدثنا إلى الناشطين،
they told us that empowerment begins with ensuring proper gender equality,
أخبرونا أن منح السلطة يبدأ بضمان المساواة المناسبة بين الجنسين،
where the women's status is established in society.
حيث يتم ترسيخ مكانة المرأة في المجتمع.
And in that way, the status of LGBT people can be affirmed as well.
وبهذه الطريقة فإنه يمكن التأكيد على مكانة المثليين.
LD: There we met Prince Manvendra.
ليزا: قابلنا هناك الأمير مانفدرا.
He's the world's first openly gay prince.
هو أول أمير مثلي الجنس في العالم يظهر علنا.
Prince Manvendra came out on the "Oprah Winfrey Show,"
ظهر الأمير مانفدرا في برنامج أوبرا وينفري الشهير،
very internationally.
بصفة عالمية.
His parents disowned him
تبرأ منه والداه
and accused him of bringing great shame to the royal family.
واتهماه بأنه ألحق العار بالعائلة الملكية.
We sat down with Prince Manvendra
جلسنا مع الأمير مانفدرا
and talked to him about why he decided to come out so very publicly.
وتحدثنا معه بشأن السبب وراء ظهوره العلني.
Here he is:
هاهو يتحدث:
(Video) Prince Manvendra: I felt there was a lot of need
(فيديو) الأمير مانفدرا: شعرت أن هناك حاجة مُلحّة
to break this stigma and discrimination which is existing in our society.
لخرق هذا العار والتمييز الموجود في مجتمعنا.
And that instigated me to come out openly and talk about myself.
وهو ما حرضني للظهور علنا والتحدث عن نفسي.
Whether we are gay, we are lesbian, we are transgender, bisexual
سواء كنا رجالًا مثليين، أو سحاقيات، أو متحولين جنسيا أو مزدوجي الميول الجنسية
or whatever sexual minority we come from,
أو أي أقلية جنسية ننحدر منها،
we have to all unite and fight for our rights.
علينا أن نتحد جميعا ونناضل من أجل حقوقنا.
Gay rights cannot be won in the court rooms,
لا يمكن تحقيق حقوق المثليين في قاعات المحاكم،
but in the hearts and the minds of the people.
ولكن في قلوب وعقول الناس.
JC: While getting my hair cut,
جيني: أثناء وجودي بصالون تجميل،
the woman cutting my hair asked me,
سألتني العاملة التي تهتم بي
"Do you have a husband?"
إن كنت متزوجةً.
Now, this was a dreaded question
كان هذا سؤالا لعينا
that I got asked a lot by locals while traveling.
أسمعه كثيرا من السكان المحليين طيلة رحلة سفري.
When I explained to her that I was with a woman instead of a man,
عندما شرحت لها أنني مرتبطة بإمرأة بدلا من رجل،
she was incredulous,
إنتابتها الشكوك،
and she asked me a lot of questions about my parents' reactions
وطرحت الكثير من الأسئلة بشأن ردة فعل والدايّ
and whether I was sad that I'd never be able to have children.
وسواء إن كنت حزينة أم لا لكوني لن أتمكن أبدا من إنجاب أطفالا.
I told her that there are no limitations to my life
أخبرتها أنه لا يوجد حدود في حياتي
and that Lisa and I do plan to have a family some day.
وأنني وليزا نخطط لتكوين عائلة يوما ما.
Now, this woman was ready to write me off
كانت هذه المرأة مستعدة للتستر عليّ وكتم ذلك
as yet another crazy Westerner.
كأي شخص آخر مجنون قادم من الغرب.
She couldn't imagine that such a phenomenon
لم تكن تستطيع أن تتخيل أن مثل هذه الظاهرة
could happen in her own country.
قد تحدث في بلدها.
That is, until I showed her the photos of the Supergays
هذا إلى أن أريتها صورا من "المثليين الخارقين"
that we interviewed in India.
الذين قابلناهم في الهند.
She recognized Prince Manvendra from television
وتعرفت على الأمير مانفدرا من التلفاز
and soon I had an audience of other hairdressers
وسرعان ما أصبح لدي جمهور آخرون من العاملات هناك
interested in meeting me.
مهتمات بمقابلتي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And in that ordinary afternoon,
وفي ظهر ذلك اليوم العادي،
I had the chance to introduce an entire beauty salon
أتيحت لي الفرصة للتحدث مع كل الموجودين في صالون التجميل وتقديم
to the social changes that were happening in their own country.
التغييرات الاجتماعية التي تحدث في مجتمعهم.
LD: From India, we traveled to East Africa,
ليزا: من الهند، اتجهنا صوب شرق أفريقيا،
a region known for intolerance towards LGBT people.
لمنطقة معروفة بتعصبها تجاه المثليين.
In Kenya, 89 percent of people who come out to their families
في كينيا، 89 بالمئة من الأشخاص الذين هجروا أُسرهم
are disowned.
وقع التبرأ منهم.
Homosexual acts are a crime and can lead to incarceration.
تعتبر ممارسة المثلية الجنسية جريمة ويمكن أن تؤدي للسجن.
In Kenya, we met the soft-spoken David Kuria.
في كينيا، قابلنا معسول الكلام ديفيد كورييا.
David had a huge mission of wanting to work for the poor
مهمة ديفيد الكبرى هي العمل لصالح الفقراء
and improve his own government.
وتحسين حكومته.
So he decided to run for senate.
لذلك قرر ترشيح نفسه لمجلس الشيوخ.
He became Kenya's first openly gay political candidate.
أصبح أول مرشح سياسي كيني مثليي الجنس.
David wanted to run his campaign without denying the reality of who he was.
أراد أن يدير حملته الإنتخابية بدون إنكار حقيقته.
But we were worried for his safety
ولكننا كنا قلقين على سلامته
because he started to receive death threats.
لأنه بدأ يتلقى تهديدات بالقتل.
(Video) David Kuria: At that point, I was really scared
(فيديو) ديفيد: في تلك المرحلة، شعرت بالخوف
because they were actually asking for me to be killed.
لأنهم كانوا يطالبون فعليا بقتلي.
And, yeah,
ونعم،
there are some people out there who do it
يوجد أشخاص يقومون بذلك
and they feel that they are doing a religious obligation.
ويشعرون أنهم يقومون بواجب ديني.
JC: David wasn't ashamed of who he was.
جيني: لم يكن دايفد يشعر بالخجل من نفسه.
Even in the face of threats,
حتى أمام التهديدات التي يتلقاها.
he stayed authentic.
بقي محافظا على أصالته.
LD: At the opposite end of the spectrum is Argentina.
ليزا: تعتبر الأرجنتين مناقضة تماما لهذا الشبح.
Argentina's a country where 92 percent of the population identifies as Catholic.
الأرجنتين دولة تبلغ فيها نسبة السكان المعتنقين الكاثولكية 92 بالمئة.
Yet, Argentina has LGBT laws that are even more progressive
مع ذلك، تملك الأرجنتين قوانين خاصة بالمثليين أكثر تقدما
than here in the US.
من الموجودة هنا في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية.
In 2010, Argentina became the first country in Latin America
في عام 2010، أصبحت الأرجنتين أول دولة في أمريكا اللاتينية
and the 10th in the world to adopt marriage equality.
والعاشرة عالميا التي تعتمد المساواة في الزواج.
There, we met María Rachid.
هناك، إلتقينا ماريا رشيد.
María was a driving force behind that movement.
كانت ماريا بمثابة القوة المحركة وراء هذه الحركة.
María Rachid (Spanish): I always say that, in reality,
ماريا رشيد (بالإسبانية): دائما ما أردد، أنه في الواقع،
the effects of marriage equality
أن تأثيرات المساواة في الزواج
are not only for those couples that get married.
لا تقتصر فقط على أولئك الذين تزوجوا.
They are for a lot of people that, even though they may never get married,
تلك القوانين موجهة للعديد من الناس حتى وإن لم يتزوجوا أبدا،
will be perceived differently by their coworkers,
سيتم النظر إليها بشكل مختلف من قبل زملاء العمل،
their families and neighbors,
وعائلاتهم وجيرانهم،
from the national state's message of equality.
حسب النداء الوطني للمساواة.
I feel very proud of Argentina
أشعر بالفخر تجاه الأرجنتين
because Argentina today is a model of equality.
لأنها تعتبر اليوم نموذجا للمساواة.
And hopefully soon,
ونأمل في القريب العاجل،
the whole world will have the same rights.
أن تصبح هذه القوانين عالميةً.
JC: When we made the visit to my ancestral lands,
جيني: عندما قمنا بزيارة أراضي أسلافي،
I wish I could have shown my parents what we found there.
تمنيت لو أمكنني أن أقدم لوالدايَ ما وجدناه هناك.
Because here is who we met:
يعود ذلك لمقابلتنا هؤلاء:
(Video) One, two, three. Welcome gays to Shanghai!
(فيديو) واحد، اثنان، ثلاثة. مرحبا بكم في شنغهاي،.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
A whole community of young, beautiful Chinese LGBT people.
مجتمع من الشباب الصينيين اللطفاء والمثليين جنسيا.
Sure, they had their struggles.
بالتأكيد، كان لديهم نضالاتهم.
But they were fighting it out.
لكنهم كانوا يواجهونها.
In Shanghai, I had the chance to speak to a local lesbian group
في شنغهاي، سنحت لي الفرصة للتحدث إلى مجموعة محلية من المثليات جنسيا
and tell them our story in my broken Mandarin Chinese.
وأخبرهم قصتي بلغتي الصينية الرديئة.
In Taipei, each time we got onto the metro,
في تايبيه، في كل مرة نركب فيها مترو الأنفاق،
we saw yet another lesbian couple holding hands.
نرى زوجين مثليين يمسكان بيد بعضهما البعض.
And we learned that Asia's largest LGBT pride event
وعلمنا أن أكبر حفل للمثليين في آسيا
happens just blocks away from where my grandparents live.
يقام على بعد عدد من الأحياء السكنية من المكان الذي يسكن فيه أجدادي.
If only my parents knew.
إذا علم والدايَ بذلك.
LD: By the time we finished our not-so-straight journey around the world,
ليزا: أنهينا مع مرور الوقت رحلتنا الملتوية حول العالم،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
we had traveled 50,000 miles
قطعنا 50،000 ميلا
and logged 120 hours of video footage.
وقمنا بتسجيل 120 ساعة من لقطات الفيديو.
We traveled to 15 countries
سافرنا إلى 15 بلدا
and interviewed 50 Supergays.
وأجرينا مقابلات مع 50 "مثلي خارق".
Turns out, it wasn't hard to find them at all.
وقد تبين أنه ليس من الصعب العثور عليهم.
JC: Yes, there are still tragedies that happen
جيني: نعم، لا تزال تحدث المآسي
on the bumpy road to equality.
خلال الرحلة الوعرة نحو تحقيق المساواة.
And let's not forget that 75 countries still criminalize homosexuality today.
ودعونا لا ننسى أنه توجد 75 دولة لازالت تجرم المثلية الجنسية إلى حد هذا اليوم.
But there are also stories of hope and courage
ولكن توجد قصص تبعث على الأمل والشجاعة
in every corner of the world.
في كل ركن من العالم.
What we ultimately took away from our journey is,
وما استنتجناه في نهاية المطاف من هذه الرحلة هو أن
equality is not a Western invention.
المساواة ليست اختراع الغرب.
LD: One of the key factors in this equality movement is momentum,
ليزا: واحد من العوامل الرئيسية في هذه الحركة لتحقيق المساواة هي القوة الدافعة،
momentum as more and more people embrace their full selves
تتشكل القوة الدافعة عندما يتمسك المزيد والمزيد من الناس بذاتهم
and use whatever opportunities they have
ويستغلون أي فرصة تأتيهم
to change their part of the world,
لتغيير جزء من العالم،
and momentum as more and more countries
كما تتشكل القوة الدافعة كلما عملت المزيد والمزيد من الدول
find models of equality in one another.
على إيجاد نماذج من المساواة مع بعضها البعض.
When Nepal protected against LGBT discrimination,
عندما تقوم نيبال بحماية المثليين ضد التمييز،
India pushed harder.
وتعمل الهند ما بوسعها لتحقيق ذلك.
When Argentina embraced marriage equality,
عندما تتبنى الأرجنتين المساواة في الزواج،
Uruguay and Brazil followed.
وتنسج على منوالها كل من الأوروجواي والبرازيل
When Ireland said yes to equality,
عندما تقول إيرلندا نعم للمساواة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
the world stopped to notice.
توقف العالم عن الملاحظة.
When the US Supreme Court makes a statement to the world
عندما تقوم المحكمة العليا بالولايات المتحدة بإصدار بيان
that we can all be proud of.
يمكننا أن نفخر به.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
JC: As we reviewed our footage,
جيني: أثناء مراجعتنا للتسجيل،
what we realized is that we were watching a love story.
أدركنا أننا كنا نشاهد قصة حبٍّ.
It wasn't a love story that was expected of me,
لم تكن قصة حب متوقعة بالنسبة لي،
but it is one filled with more freedom, adventure and love
ولكنها قصة مغمورة بمزيد من الحرية والمغامرة والحب
than I could have ever possibly imagined.
ربما أكثر مما كنت أتخيل.
One year after returning home from our trip,
بعد سنة من عودتنا من رحلتنا،
marriage equality came to California.
بدأ في كاليفورنيا العمل بالمساواة في الزواج.
And in the end, we believe, love will win out.
وآمنا أن الحب سينتصر في نهاية المطاف.
(Video) By the power vested in me,
(فيديو) حسب السلطة المخولة لي،
by the state of California
من قبل ولاية كاليفورنيا
and by God Almighty,
والرب العظيم،
I now pronounce you spouses for life.
أعلنكما زوجين طيلة الحياة.
You may kiss.
يمكنكما تبادل القبل الآن.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)